[Waco] United Confederate Veterans: Pat Cleburne Camp records, Inclusive: 1865-1937, Bulk: 1900-1918
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] United Confederate Veterans: Pat Cleburne Camp records
Inclusive: 1865-1937, Bulk: 1900-1918
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
127
United Confederate Veterans Pat Cleburne Camp No. 222, 1888 -
4 document boxes and 2 oversized folders.
The [Waco] United Confederate Veterans: Pat Cleburne Camp records consist of manuscripts collected from 1865-1937. These papers contain correspondence, financial papers, legal documents, literary productions, photographic materials, oversized materials, and other printed materials.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
The Waco chapter of the United Confederate Veterans was organized in 1888. Active until the late 1930s, it functioned much like other veterans’ organizations of the time, providing a way for veterans to remember their part in the American Civil War, financially help struggling veterans’ families, and guard the veterans’ memory of the war.
Though the camp was formed in 1888, it did not officially join the United Confederate Veterans organization until 1893. This was not unusual for the South or Texas, as many independent local organizations sprang up throughout the 1880s, and did not begin to ally with other camps until the early 1890s. A printed copy of the group’s constitution can be found in the collection.
The group wrote a constitution, held annual meetings and reunions, and participated in state and national reunions and events. Unlike the nearby Joe Johnston camp at the Confederate Reunion Grounds, there is no indication that the Pat Cleburne chapter owned their own land. It is important to note that most members of the camp probably were not native Texans, and had not served in Texas units during the Civil War. Many Southern families migrated west after the war in search of a new beginning, and Texas was the recipient of a large number of these ex-Confederates on the move. With these ties to other states, at least some Cleburne camp members attended national reunions, since there was a good chance they would know people there. State reunions became a destination as well, since some Cleburne camp veterans attended the statewide reunion in Amarillo, Texas, in 1935. The program for that reunion is in this collection.
Most of the men involved in the group had seen service in the Western theater of the Civil War, and chose to name their camp after a well-known Confederate commander, Patrick Cleburne. Cleburne had been a divisional commander in the Army of Tennessee, but was killed in 1864 at the Battle of Franklin.
The various activities of the camp were noticed by local newspapers. Though the camp did many things throughout the community, probably their most visible role was decorating the graves of their fellow soldiers on Decoration Day, the forerunner to the modern Memorial Day. Each year the veterans, in conjunction with the local chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy, would purchase fresh flowers and place them at veterans’ graves throughout Waco cemeteries. Many veterans were buried in Oakwood Cemetery, and this seemed to be the cemetery that received the most attention.
Like most United Confederate Veteran camps, the Waco chapter slowly grew less relevant as the Civil War veterans died off. There seems to be no record of a final disbanding, as the minutes end abruptly in 1937. It is possible there is a minute book or two from this camp that has not been donated yet, which could help explain the inevitable demise of Pat Cleburne Camp No. 222, United Confederate Veterans.
Scope and Content
The [Waco] United Confederate Veterans: Pat Cleburne Camp records begin in 1865 and end in 1937. Records include correspondence, financial papers, legal documents, literary productions, photographic materials, oversized materials, and other printed materials. The collection also contains an extensive collection of minutes and a large clippings file.
Arrangement
The [Waco] United Confederate Veterans: Pat Cleburne Camp records is arranged in 6 series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents, III. Literary Productions, IV. Legal Documents, V. Photographic Material, and VI. Oversized Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 127.
Related Resources
Items in related collections
[Waco] United Daughters of the Confederacy: Mary West Chapter records, Inclusive: 1866-1996, undated, Bulk: 1935-1977
Confederate Veterans collection, Inclusive: 1903-1929
Related references
Kelley, Dayton, ed. The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County, Texas. Waco: Texian, 1972.
Hattaway, Herman. “Clio’s Southern Soldiers: The United Confederate Veterans and History.” Louisiana History: The Journal of the Louisiana Historical Association, 12, 3 (1971 Summer): 213-242.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
United Confederate Veterans. Texas Division. Pat Cleburne Camp No. 222.
Places
Texas -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Social aspects.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Veterans.
Subjects
Veterans -- Confederate States of America -- History.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Minutes (Records); Photographs.; Programs.
- Correspondence, 1890-1934, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Series includes a wide variety of correspondence to and from the Waco chapter of the United Confederate Veterans. Many of the letters have something to do with “Decoration Day,” the precursor to Memorial Day. Other letters address membership matters, dues, and contact with the national office of the United Confederate Veterans. The series is in good to excellent condition.
  - Correspondence, 1890-1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1896-1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Legal Documents, 1893; 2
  General condition: Excellent.
  This small series includes a printed copy of the camp’s constitution and bylaws, as of 1893. This booklet is in excellent condition.
  - General, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Financial Documents, 1895-1936, undated; 3
  This series contains receipts for Decoration Day flower purchases and five ledger books detailing all camp purchases for 38 years. These ledgers also note all dues paid to the camp. This series is in average to good condition.
  - General, 1933-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ledger, 1895-1904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ledger, 1895-1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ledger, 1905-1908 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ledger, 1905-1924 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ledger, 1926-1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Literary Documents, 1865-1937, undated; 4
  General condition: Average.
  This series, the largest in the collection, includes programs, rosters, clippings, minutes, and printed materials generated by the camp. Most of the clippings describe United Confederate Veterans national news, general information about the Civil War, or about specific generals. Some clippings describe the Waco camp, but not many compared to the larger general clippings selection. The minutes include 3 books and 29 folders spanning 1889-1937, with no noted breaks. This series is in average to good condition.
  - General, 1865-1908, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Camp Rosters, 1907-1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Programs: Reunions, 1890-1902 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Printed Material, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Printed Material: Religious, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General Orders: 6-34, 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General Orders: 35-82, 1908-1910, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings: General, 1906-1908 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings: General, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings: General (1 of 2), 1909 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Clippings: General (2 of 2), 1909 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Clippings: Genera; (1 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Clippings: General (2 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings: General (3 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Clippings: Cleburne Camp (1 of 3), 1908-1911 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Clippings: Cleburne Camp (2 of 3), 1908-1911 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Clippings: Cleburne Camp (3 of 3), 1908-1911 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Clippings: Cleburne Camp, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Memorial Tributes, 1898-1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Book: Roster, 1925-1932 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Book: Mortuary Roster, 1917-1932 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1932-1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Book: Minutes, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Book: Minutes, 1893-1900 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Book: Minutes, 1917-1932 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Minutes (1 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Minutes (2 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Minutes (3 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Minutes (4 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Minutes (5 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Minutes (6 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Minutes (7 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Minutes (8 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Minutes (9 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Minutes (10 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Minutes (11 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Minutes (12 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Minutes (13 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Minutes (14 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Minutes (15 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Minutes (16 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Minutes (17 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Minutes (18 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Minutes (19 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Minutes (20 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Minutes (21 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Minutes (22 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Minutes (23 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Minutes (24 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Minutes (25 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Minutes (26 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Minutes (27 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Minutes (28 of 28), 1900-1917 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Photographic Materials, undated; 5
  This small series includes several photographs of Waco veterans. This series is in good to excellent condition.
  - General, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Cleburne Veterans, undated (Box [1068] OVZ, Folder 1)
- Oversized Materials, 1894-1935; 6
  This series includes several newspapers from various cities detailing the United Confederate Veterans reunions held there. The reunion ribbon is from the 1894 Waco reunion. This series is in average to excellent condition.
  - Newspapers, 1934-1935 (Box [1068] OVZ, Folder 2)